Guide to the William Blathwayt Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- Correspondence, 1646-1796; Series I; 4.0' (10 boxes)
  - Blathwayt, William, 1649?-1717
    - L (draft) to Sir Alexander Bruce, Whitehall, 169[0]/1 Mar 3
      Asking him to send a list of the officers of the recruits being raised in Scotland by Sir David Collier for service in Ireland. 1. Kincardine, Alexander Bruce, 4th Earl of, d. 1715. 2. Portmore, David Colyear, 1st Earl of, d. 1730. 3. Great Britain. Army.
    - AL (draft, in French) to Monsieur Bulan, [ca. 1695]
      About conveying respects to the court at Celle. 1. Bulan, Mons. 2. Great Britain --Foreign relations--Brunswick-- Lüneburg.
    - L (copy) to Col. Cadogan and William Aldersey, Loo, 1701 Sep 16/27 (Box 1, Folder 13)
      Chiding them for sending misleading reports about Danish troops. 1. Cadogan, William Cadogan, 1st Earl, 1672-1726. 2. Aldersey, William. 3. Great Britain--Foreign relations--Denmark.
    - AL (draft, in French) to Lord Carlingford, n.p., 1697 Aug 16
      Concerning efforts to confirm his title to family lands in Ireland. 1. Carlingford, Francis Taaffe, 3rd Earl of, 1639-1704.
    - AL (draft) for Charles II to Louis XIV (Box 1, Folder 14)
      Congratulations on the birth of the Dauphin's son.
    - AL (draft) for Charles II to Louis, the Dauphin, 1682 Aug 3
      Congratulations on the birth of his son.
    - AL (draft) for Charles II to Maria Anna, the Dauphinesse, 1682 Aug 3
      Congratulations on the birth of her son.
    - AL (draft) to George Clarke, Loo, 1698 Aug 4/14 (Box 1, Folder 15)
      Concerning the new regulation of subsistence for troops; Blathwayt wants Clarke's and Ranelagh's reaction. 1. Clarke, George, 1661-1736. 2. Ranelagh, Richard Jones, 1st Earl of, 1636?-1712. 3. Great Britain. Army.
    - Collection of 17 memoranda relating to Danish troops in English and Dutch pay
      Concerns the pay and number of Danish troops. Lists the components of the Danish forces. Many of the memoranda are addressed to Slingelandt. 1. Great Britain--Foreign relations--Denmark. 2. Netherlands-- Foreign relations--Denmark. 3. Slingelandt, Simon van, 1664-1736. 4. Spanish Succession, War of the, 1701-1714.
    - L (draft) to James Cressett, Loo, 1698 Aug 9/19 (Box 1, Folder 16)
      Concerning his negotiations for mutual aid with the Count of Brunswick-Wolfenbüttel. 1. Cressett, James, 1655?-1710. 2. Great Britain--Foreign relations --Brunswick-Wolfenbüttel.
    - AL (draft, in French) to the Marquis Doria, n.p., 1698 May 13/23
      Acknowledging the reception of Envoy Blackwell but raising the subject of Genoese treatment of English merchants. Accompanied by a draft letter of the same date to the Prince of the Vandois concerning the state of the army. 1. Doria, Marquis. 2. Blackwell, Lambert, Sir, d. 1727. 3. Great Britain--Foreign relations--Genoa. 4. Leopold, Duke of Lorraine, 1679-1729.
    - AL (draft) to Captain Elliot, Whitehall, 1700/1 Mar 25
      Giving preliminary instructions to Elliot, captain of H.M.S. Scarbrough, who later sailed to the West Indies on a special service from the king. 1. Elliot, Stephen. 2. Great Britain. Navy.
    - L (draft) to Col. [Edward] Fitz Patrick, Whitehall, 1690/1 Jan 15
      Conveying orders for receiving soldiers and prisoners. 1. Fitz Patrick, Edward. 2. Great Britain. Army.
    - AL (draft, in French) to Lord Galway, The Hague, 1695 May 16/26 (Box 1, Folder 17)
      Announcing the King's arrival at The Hague. On the same sheet is an AL (draft, in English) to Lord Lexington with the same report. 1. Ruvigny and Raineval, Henri de Massue de Ruvigny, 2nd Marquis of, 1648-1720. 2. Lexington, Robert Sutton, 2nd Baron, 1661-1723.
    - 4 AL (drafts, in French) to Lord Galway, The Hague, Whitehall, 1695 Oct 8/18-
      - Responding to the diplomatic and, Dec 17/27
      - military correspondence with directions for reforming two battalions and providing subsistence for his troops. 1. Ruvigny and Raineval, Henri de Massue de Ruvigny, 2nd Marquis of, 1648-1720. 2. Great Britain. Army.
    - AL (draft, in French) to Lord Galway, Au camp d'Attre, 1696 Aug 7/17
      About pay for Galway's troops and promotions for his officers. 1. Ruvigny and Raineval, Henri de Massue de Ruvigny, 2nd Marquis of, 1648-1720. 2. Great Britain. Army.
    - 3 AL (drafts, in French) and 2 letters (drafts, in French) to Lord Galway, Whitehall, Loo, 1698 Apr 19-
      - Concerning French Reformed officers, Sep 6/16
      - in Ireland and O'Donnell's Irish pension. 1. Ruvigny and Raineval, Henri de Massue de Ruvigny, 2nd Marquis of, 1648-1720. 2. Great Britain. Army. French Reformed officers. 3. O'Donnell, Hugh Balldearg, d. 1704.
    - 2 L (drafts) to Col. Gibson, Whitehall, 1690/1 Mar 7 (Box 1, Folder 18)
      - Concerning the state of the garrison, Mar 10
      - at Portsmouth. 1. Gibson, John, Sir, 1637-1717. 2. Great Britain. Army.
    - AL (draft, in French) to Mons. Ginchet, Whitehall, 1690/1 Feb 14
      Concerning pay for troops in Ireland. 1. Ginchet, Mons. 2. Great Britain. Army.
    - AL (draft, in French) to Baron Goerz, Loo
      Conveying the respects of the King. 1. Goerz, Baron de. 2. Great Britain--Foreign relations--Hanover.
    - L (copy) to Hugh Greg, Loo, 1695 Oct 4 (Box 1, Folder 19)
      Concerning a maritime dispute with Denmark. 1. Greg, Hugh, d. 1702. 2. Great Britain--Foreign relations--Denmark.
    - 2 L (drafts) to Hugh Greg, Loo, 1701 Sep 24
      - About the arrears of subsidies to, Oct 8
      - Denmark and the conditions under which Danish troops will be paid. 1. Greg, Hugh, d. 1702. 2. Great Britain--Foreign relations--Denmark.
    - AL (draft) to the Chancellor of the Exchequer, n.p., 1698 Oct 14/24
      Concerning Montagu's role in settling the forfeiture of Sir John Friend's share in the Phoenix Brewhouse. 1. Halifax, Charles Montagu, 1st Earl of, 1661-1715. 2. Friend, John, Sir, d. 1696.
    - L (draft) to Capt. Hamilton, Whitehall, 1691 Mar 31 (Box 1, Folder 20)
      Acquainting him with orders to ship soldiers from Ireland to Plymouth in an unprotected convoy. 1. Hamilton, Capt. 2. Great Britain. Army.
    - AL (draft) to the Mayor of Harwich, Whitehall, 1702 Dec 27
      About using Harwich for shipping horses for the use of troops in Holland. 1. Harwich, England. 2. Great Britain. Army.
    - 2 AL (drafts, in French) to Anthonij Heinsius, Loo, 1692 Apr 10
      - Writing to Heinsius (the Pensioner), n.d.
      - about orders for marine officers, preparations for war, and refugees. 1. Heinsius, Anthonij, 1641-1720. 2. Grand Alliance, War of the, 1689-1697. 3. Great Britain--Foreign relations--Netherlands.
    - 2 AL (drafts) to [John] Henley, Whitehall, 1691 Apr 30 (Box 1, Folder 21)
      - Concerning army provisions in, May 9
      - Bristol; horses are to be shipped to Ireland; recruits are to be given "warm meat thrice a week;" oats and cheese. 1. Henley, John. 2. Great Britain. Army.
    - L (copy) to Richard Hill, Before Namur, 1695 Aug 15
      About providing subsistence for the officers and soldiers of the garrisons taken by the French. Hill was deputy paymaster of the troops. 1. Hill, Richard, 1655-1727. 2. Great Britain. Army.
    - 2 AL (drafts) and 1 letter (copy) to Richard Hill, Loo, 1698 Jun 16-
      - Providing directions for meeting, Sep 12
      - military costs, for dispatching regiments of French Protestants to Ireland, and for ignoring Ailesbury's Jacobite enclave in Brussells. 1. Hill, Richard, 1655-1727. 2. Great Britain. Army. 3. Great Britain. Army--French Reformed Officers. 4. Ailesbury, Thomas Bruce, 2nd Earl of, 1655?-1741.
    - L (copy) to Mr. Jenkins, Whitehall, 1703/4 Feb 28 (Box 1, Folder 22)
      Sending Jenkins his deputation as deputy Auditor and surveyor general of Jamaica. 1. Jenkins, Henry. 2. Jamaica-- History.
    - 6 AL (drafts) and 1 letter (copy) to Lord Lexington, v.p., 1694/5 Jan 8/18-
      - Lexington was English Envoy to the, 1695/6 Jan 3/13
      - Emperor in Vienna. Blathwayt writes about the Queen's death, the Comte de Frise's unwarranted disgrace in the Imperial court, proposal to make Frise an envoy to Prince Louis de Baden, Lexington's wish to have Stepney in Vienna, continuing the Grand Alliance, the bombardment of Brussells, and Frise's reconciliation with the Emperor. The letters of Aug 12 and 16 have been partially printed in H. M. Sutton's The Lexington Papers, pp. 106-08. 1. Lexington, Robert Sutton, 2nd Baron, 1661-1723. 2. Friesen, Julius Heinrich, Count von. 3. Mary II, Queen of Great Britain, 1662-1694. 4. Great Britain--Foreign relations--Holy Roman Empire. 5. Stepney, George, 1663-1707. 6. Great Britain. Treaties, etc., 1694-1702 (William III).
    - "List of papers relating to the Expedition to the Baltic in the year 1700", [ca. 1700]
      Memorandum, prepared for William Blathwayt and docketed by him. 1. Rooke, George, Sir, 1650-1709. 2. Great Britain--Foreign relations --Sweden.
    - L (copy, in French) to Mons. des Loges, Whitehall, 1691 May 5 (Box 1, Folder 23)
      Concerning preparations for a convoy for Ireland. 1. Loges, Mons. des. 2. Great Britain. Army.
    - 3 AL (drafts) to the Lords Justices, 1698 Aug 19/29-
      - The Aylmer and West Indies, Dec 10
      - squadrons; French Reformed troops in Ireland; the king's wariness about the move in the Irish House of Commons for sole right of originating money bills. 1. Great Britain. Lords Justices. 2. Great Britain. Army. French Reformed Officers. 3. Great Britain. Navy. 4. Aylmer, Matthew Aylmer, Baron, d. 1720. 5. Ireland. Parliament, 1698.
    - 1 AL (draft) and 4 letters (drafts) to the Lords Justices of Ireland, The Hague, 1698 Aug 1-
      - Concerning places for Reformed, Oct 21/31
      - Officers and other military matters, and prorogation and money bills in the Irish Parliament. 1. Ireland. Lords Justices and Council. 2. Great Britain. Army. 3. Ireland. Parliament, 1698.
    - 3 letters (drafts) to Mons. Marmonde (in French), Loo, 1699 Aug 4/14- (Box 1, Folder 24)
      - Concerns the establishment of the, Sep 1/11
      - identity of one William O'Bryan.
    - AL (draft, in French) to Maximilian II, the Elector of Bavaria, n.p., 1698 Dec 10
      Concerning efforts to maintain peace in Europe. 1. Maximilian II Emanuel, Elector of Bavaria, 1662-1726.
    - AL (draft) to the Mayor and Corporation Newport, Isle of Wight, 1692 Dec 26
      Declining the position offered to him by the corporation, Blathwayt recommends his "near kinsman," Brigadier Leveson. 1. Leveson, Richard, d. 1696.
    - AL (draft, in French) to Mons. Norff, Whitehall, 1695 Dec 5/15
      About subsidies for troops and ordinance. 1. Norff, Mons. 2. Grand Alliance, War of the, 1689-1697.
    - AL (draft, in French) to Mons. Odijck n.p., 1697/8 Mar 4/14 (Box 1, Folder 25)
      Expressing surprise that Odijck had not received payment for his services. 1. Odijck, William Adrian de Nassau, Lord of
    - AL (draft, in French) to the Comte d'Ossonville, Dierin, 1698 Nov 1/11
      Explaining the effect of peace on the King's policy. 1. Ossonville, Comte d'.
    - AL (draft) to Lord Paget, The Hague, 1692/3 Mar 25
      Conveying some instructions for Paget as Ambassador in Turkey. 1. Paget, William Paget, 6th Baron, 1637-1713. 2. Great Britain--Foreign relations--Turkey.
    - AL (draft, in French) to Mr. Pincier, n.p., 1698 May 27
      Concerning a subsidy for the Duke of Holstein. 1. Pincier, Mons. 2. Friedrich IV, Duke of Holstein-Gottorp, 1670-1702.
    - 2 extracts (in Dutch) to [Lord Portland], n.p., 1697 May 1, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 26)
      Concerning Lord Clancarty's estate. 1. Portland, William Bentinck, 1st Earl of, 1649-1709. 2. Clancarty, Donough Maccarthy, 4th Earl of, 1668-1734.
    - Warrant naming Edward Randolph deputy surveyor general of customs in New England: contemporary manuscript copy, 1691 Feb
      Blathwayt held the right to name his deputies under a patent from Charles II. 1. Randolph, Edward, 1632?-1703. 2. New England--History--Colonial period, ca. 1600-1775.
    - Letter (draft) to the Earl of Ranelagh, n.p., 1698 Oct 31
      Reporting no progress on a request of Ranelagh. 1. Ranelagh, Richard Jones, 1st Earl of, 1636?-1712.
    - Regulations for the precedence of regiments: contemporary manuscript copy, Roosbeck, 1694 Jun 10
      1. Great Britain. Army.
    - L (draft) to John Robinson, The Hague, 1695 Oct 5 (Box 1, Folder 27)
      Concerning an English encounter by mistake with a Swedish Man of War. 1. Robinson, John, Bishop of London, 1650-1723. 2. Great Britain--Foreign relations--Sweden.
    - 4 AL (drafts) and 1 letter (copy) to John Robinson, Loo, The Hague, 1698 Aug 9/19-
      - Directions for his negotiations with, Dec 6
      - Sweden for an alliance with England; there is some use of cypher. 1. Robinson, John, Bishop of London, 1650-1723. 2. Great Britain--Foreign relations--Sweden.
    - 3 AL (drafts, in French) to Baron Saffig, London, 1693/4 Feb 5-
      - The king recognizes and appreciates, 1695 Nov 26
      - the sacrifice of his country on behalf of the Grand Alliance. 1. Saffig, Baron de la Leyen. 2. Grand Alliance, War of the, 1689-1697.
    - AL (draft) to the Duke of Schomberg, Breda, 1695 Sep 16 (Box 2, Folder 28)
      The king wishes him to discover why not all companies are up to full strength. 1. Schomberg, Meinhard Schomberg, 3rd Duke of, 1641-1719. 2. William III, King of Great Britain, 1650-1702. 3. Great Britain. Army.
    - L (draft) to the Duke of Schomberg, n.p., 1698 Aug 4/14
      Assuring him that the king has written a recommendation for his cause in the Imperial Chamber. 1. Schomberg, Meinhard Schomberg, 3rd Duke of, 1641-1719. 2. Great Britain--Foreign relations--Holy Roman Empire.
    - AL (draft, in French) to M. Schuylunburg, The Hague, 1695 Sep 1/11
      Ordering the payment of a monthly pension to the Countess of Solms. 1. Schuylenburg, W. S. 2. Solms-Braunfels, Countess of
    - AL (draft) to the Duke of Shrewsbury, Dieren, 1696 Aug 31 (Box 2, Folder 29)
      Forwarding "good words and promises" to the bank for the supply and sending the royal order for dispatching the Mediterranean squadron. 1. Shrewsbury, Charles Talbot, Duke of, 1660-1718. 2. Bank of England. 3. Great Britain. Navy.
    - AL (draft) to the Duke of Shrewsbury, n.p., 1696 Sep 2/12
      The king intends to return before the opening of Parliament; he has not said anything about recalling Lord Paget; he is not dissatisfied with Sir George Rooke; he will study the dispute between Erle and the Admiralty when he returns. 1. Shrewsbury, Charles Talbot, Duke of, 1660-1718. 2. Great Britain. Parliament, 1696. 3. Paget, William Paget, 6th Baron, 1637-1713. 4. Rooke, George, Sir, 1650-1709. 5. Erle, Thomas, 1650?-1720. 6. Great Britain. Admiralty. I. William III, King of Great Britain, 1650-1702.
    - AL (draft) to the Duke of Shrewsbury, n.p., 1697 May 11 (Box 2, Folder 29a)
      Reporting a feverish indisposition of the king, and sending his orders for the immediate dispatch of the eight battalions for Williamstadt (in response to a query of Lords Justices, cf. C.S.P.D. 1697, p. 140). 1. Shrewsbury, Charles Talbot, Duke of, 1660-1718. 2. William III, King of Great Britain, 1650-1702. 3. Great Britain. Army. 4. Great Britain. Lords Justices.
    - AL (draft) to the Duke of Shrewsbury, Luylestein, 1697 May 14
      Reporting the full recovery of the king from his illness. 1. Shrewsbury, Charles Talbot, Duke of, 1660-1718. 2. William III, King of Great Britain, 1650-1702.
    - AL (draft) to the Duke of Shrewsbury, Camp near Genap, 1697 Jun 20 (Box 2, Folder 29b)
      The king is pleased to follow Shrewsbury's recommendation for Mr. Baber to succeed Mr. Haines as Governor of Jamaica; Baber will be permitted to act by deputy. 1. Shrewsbury, Charles Talbot, Duke of, 1660-1718. 2. Jamaica--History 3. Haines, Mr. 4. Baber, John.
    - Letter (draft) to the Duke of Shrewsbury, n.p., 1697 Jul 8
      Concerning Cressett's role as envoy. 1. Shrewsbury, Charles Talbot, Duke of, 1660-1718. 2. Cressett, James, 1655?-1710.
    - AL (draft) to the Duke of Shrewsbury, n.p., 1697 Jul 15
      Concerning Povey's appointment as clerk of the Privy Council. 1. Shrewsbury, Charles Talbot, Duke of, 1660-1718. 2. Povey, John, d. 1705. 3. Great Britain. Privy Council.
    - AL (draft) to the Duke of Shrewsbury, n.p., 1697 Jul 25
      Concerning the appointment of Povey as Clerk of the Privy Council and James Vernon, junior, as clerk in extraordinary; the king supports Lord Carlingford in all his Irish concerns. 1. Shrewsbury, Charles Talbot, Duke of, 1660-1718. 2. Povey, John, d. 1705. 3. Vernon, James, d. 1756. 4. Carlingford, Francis Traffe, 3rd Earl of, 1635-1704.
    - Letter (copy) to the Duke of Shrewsbury, Cockleberg, 1697 Jul 29 (Box 2, Folder 29c)
      Manchester should be dispatched to Venice; the king allows favorable words in the letters of revocation for Colonel Fletcher as governor of New York; the villainy of Count Boselli. 1. Shrewsbury, Charles Talbot, Duke of 1660-1718. 2. Manchester, Charles Montagu, 1st Duke of, 1660?-1722. 3. Fletcher, Benjamin, fl. 1692-1698. 4. Boselli, Count.
    - AL (draft) to the Duke of Shrewsbury, Loo
      The king agrees that Manchester should be allowed a Secretary for his embassy and approves Colonel Wolseley's petition for lands in Ireland. 1. Shrewsbury, Charles Talbot, Duke of, 1660-1718. 2. Manchester, Charles Montagu, 1st Duke of, 1660?-1722. 3. Wolseley, William, 1640?-1697.
    - AL (draft) to the Duke of Shrewsbury, Loo
      Delay in decision for successor to Davenant as Exempt of the Yeoman of the Guards; Major General Trelawny's warrant. 1. Shrewsbury, Charles Talbot, Duke of, 1660-1718. 2. Davenant, Charles, 1656-1714. 3. Trelawny, Charles, 1654-1731.
    - Letter (copy) to the Duke of Shrewsbury, n.p., 1697 Aug 22
      The king approves of Stanyan as Manchester's secretary. 1. Shrewsbury, Charles Talbot, Duke of, 1660-1718. 2. Manchester, Charles Montagu, 1st Duke of, 1660?-1722. 3. Stanyan, Abraham, 1669?-1732.
    - AL (draft) to the Duke of Shrewsbury, Loestdike, 1697 Sep 2/12
      Trelawny's warrant; the Czar accepted an invitation to dine with the king, but then excused himself. 1. Shrewsbury, Charles Talbot, Duke of, 1660-1718. 2. Trelawny, Charles, 1654-1731. 3. Peter I, the Great, emperor of Russia, 1672-1725.
    - L (draft) to the Duke of Shrewsbury, The Hague, 1698 Nov 22
      Concerning Sir W. Carstin [?]. 1. Shrewsbury, Charles Talbot, 1st Duke of, 1660-1718.
    - AL (draft, in French) to Simon van Slingelandt, Whitehall, 1698 Apr 22 (Box 2, Folder 30)
      Concerning the proportion of the king's expenses to be met by England and the Netherlands. 1. Slingelandt, Simon van, 1664-1736. 2. Great Britain--Foreign relations--Netherlands.
    - 4 AL (drafts, in French) to the Comte de Solms, Whitehall, Loo, 1691/2 Feb 5-
      - Concerning the payment of English, Apr 4
      - troops and the provisions of horses and rations. 1. Solms-Braunfels, Heinrich Maastricht Solms, Count of, 1636- 1693. 2. Great Britain. Army.
    - L (extract) to Alexander Stanhope and Paul Methuen, 1697 Oct 2 (Box 2, Folder 31)
      Communicating to them the tenth article of the Treaty of Ryswick with instructions to inform English merchants in Spain and Portugal. 1. Stanhope, Alexander, 1639-1707. 2. Methuen, Paul, Sir, 1672-1757. 3. Ryswick, Peace of, 1697.
    - L (draft) to Alexander Stanhope, Loo, 1698 Sep 18/28
      Arranging a Spanish honor for the Duke of Aremberg at the request of William III. 1. Stanhope, Alexander, 1639-1707. 2. Aremberg, Leopold, Duke of, d. 1754.
    - L (copy) to Alexander Stanhope, Loo, 1699 Oct 2
      Reporting that the Spanish Ambassador to England, the Marquis de Canales, has been given eighteen days to leave the country for presenting a memorial appealing to the Parliament and people against the king; Stanhope will have to forfeit his post as envoy in Spain; news of the failure of the Darien scheme. Accompanied by a holograph draft of the letter. 1. Stanhope, Alexander, 1639-1717. 2. Great Britain--Foreign relations --Spain. 3. Darien. Scots' Colony.
    - 1 AL (draft) and 3 letters (drafts) to Alexander Stanhope, Loo, Breda, 1701 Aug 8/19-
      - Concerning negotiations with the King, Oct 3
      - of Poland, the Czar of Russia, and about the Spanish succession. Stanhope was envoy to the United Provinces during this period. 1. Stanhope, Alexander, 1639-1707. 2. Great Britain--Foreign relations --Poland. 3. Great Britain--Foreign relations--Spain. 4. Great Britain --Foreign relations--Russia.
    - 3 AL (drafts) and 1 letter (draft) to George Stepney, The Hague, Loo, 1698 Aug 5- (Box 2, Folder 32)
      - Informing him of Schonenberg's new, Dec 6
      - powers in Spain; responding to news that the Elector of Brandenberg wishes to enter into closer alliance with England; and giving instructions to Stepney for his diplomatic mission in Prussia and Brandenberg. 1. Stepney, George, 1663-1707. 2. Schonenberg, Francis. 3. Great Britain--Foreign relations --Brandenburg.
    - ALS to George Stepney, Whitehall, 170[1] Mar 11 (Box 2, Folder 32a)
      Reports on the passing of the Right of Succession and asks Stepney to congratulate the family of the Electress Sophia of Hanover. 1. Sophie, consort of Ernest Augustus, elector of Hanover, 1630- 1714.
    - ALS to George Stepney, Whitehall, 1701 Mar 20
      Discusses the reaction in Parliament to the second Treaty of Partition. Mentions Davenant's Essays upon the Balance of Power and other matters. 1. Davenant, Charles, 1656-1714.
    - ALS to George Stepney, Whitehall, 1701 [May?] 20
      Sends news of Parliamentary proceedings to Stepney, who has just arrived in Vienna. Mentions Count Wratislav, Holland, the Holy Roman Emperor, Parliament's reduction of William III's civil list and a rumor that German forces have beaten the French in Italy.
    - ALS to [George Stepney], Whitehall, 1701 Jun 6
      On difficulties between England and the Holy Roman Empire; Stepney's good fortune in being abroad during his friends' (Portland, Somers, Orford, and Halifax) impeachment; troops being sent to Holland, and Blathwayt's own preparations for the winter there.
    - ALS to George Stepney, Whitehall, 1701 Jun 13 (Box 2, Folder 32b)
      On the House of Commons' action towards the Holy Roman Empire, newly appointed governors of New York and Massachusetts, Stepney's good fortune in being abroad during the impeachment of his friends (Portland, Somers, Orford, and Halifax), and Marlborough's troops in Holland. 1. Clarendon, Edward Hyde, 3rd Earl of, 1661-1723. 2. Bellamont, Richard Coote, 1st Earl of, 1636-1701.
    - ALS to George Stepney, Whitehall, 1701 Jun 27
      Hopes that Stepney can visit the king in Holland; news of appointments and vacancies.
    - ALS to [George Stepney], The Hague, [1701] Jul 4/15
      He has just arrived on the continent with the King, as has Marlborough.
    - ALS to [George Stepney], Breda, [1701] Jul 21
      About Stepney's proposal that William keep an army of 20,000 men on the lower Rhine; the possibility of using Hussars; their eagerness for news of the Imperial Army's success in Italy.
    - ALS to George Stepney, Breda, [1701] Jul 21
      "We are all here in a State of Warr tho in Peace...." Describes Count Wratislau as a man of honor, but less fitted to the court than Count Auersperg. Describes his children's situation at Utrecht. Mentions sending two more regiments to the West Indies. 1. Auersperg, Graf.
    - ALS to George Stepney, on boat between Utrecht and [?], [1701] Aug 1
      Blathwayt is reviewing troops with William. Stepney's letters to William were well received. William will not mediate the peace between Sweden and Poland with Louis XIV. Mentions Prince Eugene's bravery, D'Avaux, and other matters. 1. Louis XIV, King of France, 1638-1715. 2. Avaux, Jean-Antoine de Mesmes, Comte d', 1673-1709.